Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 2 -- Letters to Franklin 1777 January-1778 March Mss.B.F85inventory02
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 23; L.S. 1p.; Sorbonne
    Sending a letter by M. de Chalut which was delivered to him by mistake.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Lafargue, J. Paris
    Enclosing a letter and certificate of a friend; begs for an answer to his request.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Soleau, Lieut. Besançon
    France being at peace, offers his services to the Colonies; his military rank and service; his only conditions are a leave of absence, the command of a company of cavalry and the cost of his voyage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 25; A.L.S. 4p.; Baussay, Elias de, Dutch agent of Elector of Trier. La Haye
    Heard with pleasure that his letter of May 22d was delivered to Franklin. Account of affairs in Holland relative to the Colonies. Sir Joseph Yorke's attempt to gain over to England two regiments belonging to the Prince de Waldeck; reasons why this is likely to prove unsuccessful. Amsterdam entirely in favor of the Americans; her late petitions to increase her navy. Death of his old friend, Mr. Jacob Henry Chabanct. Rupture between England and France regarded as inevitable.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 25; A.L.S. 4p.; Barry, Amelia. Tunis
    Fearing that he had not received her last letter of July 3d, sends a copy of it by a sure hand.
    [See page 264.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Lalaisse, —. Toul
    Desires to go to America and serve in the army; his reasons are not mercenary; wishes to know the conditions, treatment etc. Many of his comrades desire to follow him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Desires the enclosed letter sent to Mr. Holker if Franklin approves it. Reminds him of his intended visit to the salt works at Nantes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Quane, O'Reilly de. Aumale
    Though unknown to Franklin, has the greatest admiration and affection for him. Has made a translation of "Considerations on the Measures Carrying on with Respect to the British Colonies in North America"; desires to dedicate it to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 26; Valentz, Jno. Paris
    Was formerly an inhabitant of Pennsylvania; compelled ten years before on account of his debts to quit the province; his hard struggle ever since; desires to return and throw himself on the mercy of his creditors, also wishes to take a commission in the Continental service; has been an officer in the provincial service; personally acquainted with General Washington. Has not a sou in the world; begs Franklin to assist him in procuring a passage; his claim on Franklin's kindness as a fellow Mason; member of St. John's Lodge, No. 2, in Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Penet, Pierre. Nantes
    The accompanying letter is from his associate, M. Pharne; much regrets that Franklin does not deem his letters worthy of any reply.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Wickes, Lambert. St. Malo
    Acknowledging favor of the 22nd inst. The Dolphin will not be suffered to leave the port until further orders from Paris. Captain Johnston arrested at Morlaix and cannot get away without permission; desires a line from Franklin. Question whether the French soldiers will be suffered to ship with them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Concerning Holland's refusal to cede to England the two regiments of the Prince de Waldeck; intrigue on the part of Sir Jos[eph Yorke].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Coder, Henry
    By September expects to deliver to any specified port the 1,300 completed uniforms that have been ordered. Desires no salary, but merely the opportunity of serving the United Colonies, where he has decided to live or die.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Wommrad, Lieut. Mannbeim
    Studied engineering since his earliest years; his military services; desires to fight for the American cause; wishes to know what arrangements must be made.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 28; A.L.S. 4p.; Grenus, Col. Tissot. Geneva
    Concerning two volumes of military works which he cannot afford to have printed. Asks Franklin's help; every soldier ought to have a copy of his work.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 28; A.L.S. 4p.; Cavoleau, -----. Lucon
    Begs Franklin to save him from the borrors of despair and procure him a position in the American army or at least to tell him the means of carrying out his desire. Tells a long tale of misfortune; loss of money; perfidy of friends. M. Tardiveau, who is about to leave for America, under Franklin's auspices, is the only relation and friend he has in the world.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Lecoq, -----. Paris
    A friend of his anxious to know to whom he must apply to procure a commission as captain of a privateer; his friend's vessel equipped with ten cannon, arms and men in proportion.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Temple, J. Richmond Green, Surrey
    Mr. Izard goes with his family to reside in France till a chance offers to cross to America; he has been detained for two years, like himself, in the hope that England would not remain so " madly blind " to its own interests. Consults Franklin on the advisability of following Mr. Izard's example, with his wife and two boys. Gloom caused by late accounts from America; report of the total destruction of the Newfoundland fisheres has reduced the citizens to sullen silence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Dehaistre, -----. Paris.
    Having heard that M. Deane has been commissioned to make purchase for the Colonies, offers his services for the kitchen utensils.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning a complaint against Capt. Wickes by certain of his crew, who claim prize money; encloses the Captain's explanation [2 p.]. The capture of Brunswick confirmed. General Tryon and Colonel Walcott dead of wounds received at Danbury.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 30; A.L.S. 1p. 2p.; Guérin, -----. Paris
    Sends him an extract of a letter, which he received from his brother; begs Franklin to take immediate action in this matter with M. de Sartine so that by his prompt orders the mischief may be averted.
    The extract concerns a misunderstanding with the Minister of the Marine.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 30; A.L.S. 3p.; Rânes, Charles-Pierre-François d'Argouges, comte de. Auch
    A friend of his desires to serve the American cause and has asked him to find out from Franklin the means necessary to carry out this plan; his rank is high and he will inherit a large fortune. Le Marquis de Lafayette is not the only example of a man of the first quality crossing the sea to devote his life to the American cause.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 30; L.S. 2p.; Massequan, -----. Nice
    Wrote Franklin on the 7th of June and sent him the petition of one Francis Fowler who desired a commission to command a privateer; has received no answer. Wishes to know what Capt. Fowler may expect.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Merle, Frederic
    Sends him some verses in praise of their brave islanders; trusts Franklin may find them worthy of being offered to their brother insurgents.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Lehsveld, Van F. Leyden
    Had the honor to write Franklin December, 1774, touching his letters to Mr. Brownrigg, upon the use of oil to still the waves, and in April 1775, sent him six copies of a paper he published on the same subject; believes that he never received either letters or papers. His friend, Professor Tollius, is at present in Paris and will present Franklin with a copy of his Dutch piece translated into French.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Wickes, Lambert. St. Malo
    The bearer is M. le Baron de Cadignun, who has rendered him every service in his power; this is merely to introduce him to Franklin, as he has no favors to ask, and does not desire to go to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Feutry, Aimé Ambroise Joseph
    Desires to be associated in some way with the Philosophical Society of Philadelphia, if only as a correspondent.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Wickes, Lambert. St. Malo
    Acknowledging his favor of July 25th. French seamen now in jail; gave themselves up voluntarily. Steps he has taken relative to the prize brig. Will be ready for sea as soon as permission is given them to start; Capt. Johnston in a like situation at Morlaix.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Carantènè, ----- de (Paul de Carantaine?)
    Desires to offer his services to America; his age, military experience and rank; conditions on which he will join the army; understands German as well as French.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 1; Mem. 1p.; -----, -----. Paris
    Proposed contract for purchasing a vessel.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Du Pont de Nemours, Pierre Samuel. Paris
    Opened the accompanying packet which was addressed to him, but intended for Franklin; no longer enjoys, as he once did, the confidence of Government, and letters sent to him are no longer postage free; is only too glad to be of any service, but suggests that Franklin's correspondents should put some mark on their letters so that he will know them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Paddack, Seth. Marseilles
    Came over from Philadelphia with the promise of having a good ship at Nantes, fitted out in a warlike manner, to go back in; found it all a farce; after various vicissitudes, is now anxious to get a private ship to return home in; should be glad to Franklin's assistance to obtain a commission for him in his country's service; will never bring disgrace on his family; devoted to his country, though Franklin once doubted it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 3; A.L.S. 2p.; N-----, F-----. St. Omer
    Is an officer in the British army; desires to known if his services will be acceptable to the United States; positions he has held in the English army; desires, on landing in America, to receive a regiment with the rank of colonel, and the expenses of passage for himself and servants. Gen. Gates a great friend of his. Expects Franklin to observe the greatest secrecy on this matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Haineville, Mme
    Her son, in the American army, has been taken prisoner by the Englsih; begs Franklin to allow her an interview that she may tell him her trouble.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Wickes, Lambert. St. Malo
    The bearer is M. Becard, of St. Malo, who desires to enter into the American trade; as he has been of great service to him (Wickes) hopes Franklin will render him any service in his power.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 5; A.L.S. 3p.; Wildrik, W. Namur
    Surgeon in the service of the Low Countries; desires to give his services to the American army and take a position in one of their hospitals.
    (In French and Latin.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 6; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Quane, Mlle — de. Paris
    Begs Franklin to answer the enclosed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Devienne, Marquis. Doullens
    Desires to joint the Marquis de Lafayette to whom he carries the best recommendations.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 August 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Giving Capt. Hereaud, commander of the Mercury, the highest praise in the performance of his duty.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 August 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing M. de Folignè, commander of a French frigate belonging to M. Montieu.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Duvaunoel, -----. Gaillon
    Offers his services in the line of business in France and other countries; has letters of recommendation from M. Turgot.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 7; L.S. 1p.; Bingham, William. Saint Pierre
    Introducing M. de Karsaint who commands one of his Majesty's armed vessels that has been some time past stationed in 'these seas'; circumstances would not permit him to refuse this letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Sauvage, Laiquel. Calais
    A shoemaker offers Franklin 2,000 pairs of shoes at three francs, twelve centimes a pair. Concerning a debt due him by an officer in the service. Cheapness of shirts in his province.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Wickes, Lambert. St. Malo
    Ready to sail; their powder will not be delivered without a positive order from the Minister; Capt. Johnston only waiting for Franklin's orders to depart from Morlaix; the bearer is anxious to sail with him to America; promised not to take any French persons on board and carry them off without permission from the Judge of the Admiralty; is in the same quandary with regard to the Chevalier de Cheffontain, recommended by Franklin. Has manned his vessel from the crew of a disarmed American privateer; cruel treatment of their captain in England.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 August 7; L.S. B[enjamin] Harrison, R[ober]t Morris, James Lovell. 3p.; The Continental Congress, Committee of Foreign Affairs. Philadelphia
    Military affairs in America. Loss of Ticonderoga.
    (In triplicate.)
    Printed in Diplom. Corres., Wharton, II, 373.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Ponteney, -----. Versailles
    Asks for an interview to arrange certain business matters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 8; N. in 3d P. 1p.; de Germany, M. Paris
    Requests Dr. Franklin to forward an enclosed letter to its destination.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 8; A.L.S. 3p.; Foucault, Jean-Simon-David de. Plombiéres
    Health of his wife much improved. Good news from America; defeat of Cornwallis by General Putnam and the abandonment of Brunswick with a loss of 3,000 men; pursuit of the fleeting army by General Putunam. Short of money, his stay being unexpectedly long; asks Franklin for an advance of one hundred louis. Expects to go to asks Franklin for an advance of one hundred louis. Expects to go to Switzerland; asks for Franklin's orders.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 8; A.L.S. 3p.; Champigny, Jean Bochard de. Amsterdam
    Franklin subscribed to his History of England. Sends the first volume; reasons for dedicating it to Prince Ferdinand of Brunswick. Offers him the first two volumes of his translation of the "Histoire des rois de Danemark de la Maison d'Oldenbourg."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Réal, -----. Calais.
    Concerning the unfortunate circumstances of two sailors from Boston, Joseph Peach and William Smith, who were taken prisoners by the English; they escaped, seized a boat and arrived finally at Calais; desires Franklin's permission to enable them to sell the boat they arrived in, which the officers of the port have made them abadon. Calais very often a refuge for Americans who escape from prison.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Has a small sloop called the Montgomery, which he proposes to send back, armed, to America; not having a commission, applies to Franklin for one. Has two vessels that will sail direct for the continent in fifteen days; any commands that Franklin may care to transmit by them shall be duly attended to.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Berard, -----. Paris.
    Has a letter to deliver from Captain Wickes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Haineville, Mme. Paris
    Begs Franklin to take her son under his protection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 10; L. in 3d person. 2p.; Morand, Dr Jean François Clèment. Paris
    Has examined the list of descriptions of arts and trades sent him by Dr. Franklin. Sends him his work, "L'Art d'exploiter les mines de Charbon de terre." Is marking a collection of engraved portraits of the scholars composing the Academy of Science; desires Franklin's portrait for this work.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 11; L.S. 4p.; Bingham, William. St Pierre
    Important news received; junction between Gen. Howe's and Gen. Cornwallis's troops at Brunswick; marched as far as Somerset, then retraced their steps; Gen. Washington attacked them, whereupon they retreated to Amboy and thence embarked for New York; they pillaged and destroyed almost the whole town of Burnswick; advantages to be derived from this affair. Destruction of the Newfoundland fisheries by two Continental frigates and a number of privateers. Capture of the frigate "Fox" by Capt. Manley. Reasons why he supplied Mr. Davis and M. Baussancourt with money. Encloses a letter relative to the differences between British and Hessian troops. Ultimate destination of the sloop of war, the Marie Catherine.
    1777. September 9. — News of Gen. Howe's departure from New York; speculation as regards his ultimate destination. Thinks the New England States will have to bear the whole weight of the winter's campaign. Capture of Capt. Manly and his prize.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Nicholson, Samuel. Nantes
    Just setting out for St. Malo where Mr. Williams thinks he had better spend about three weeks in order to be out of the way while the new ship is being built; has promised Capt. Tanner the master's berth and a lieutenantcy to Mr. Dillaway; can easily get a crew. Desertions from the Randolph on account of sickness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Bedout, James. Bordeaux
    Asks for a commission from the Congress to empower him to cruise against the English; describes his vessel; references he can furnish.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Martin, Lieut. Ile de Rè
    Is a lieutenant in the Fifth South Carolina Battalion. Has orders to wait on Franklin and receive his commands before returning.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 August 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Some foundation for the reports from America concerning the affair at Burnswick.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Will settle the affair between Capt. Wickes and his men. Concerning M. de Kerguelen's plan to fit out a vessel of war in the service of the United States; has given a letter to the Baron de Gessè who will open the whole plan to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing the Baron de Gessè.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Whitehead, Charles. Boulogne-sur-Mer
    Thoroughly convinced of the justice of the American cause. As a member of the Corporation of London, has constantly voted in opposition to a profligate and corrupt Court. Lost the greater part of his fortune in the present war; has only his person, therefore, to offer; is a descendant of the great Admiral Benbow; begs for a commission in the service of America with instructions how to act. His only tie is a young daughter dearer to him than life.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Verseüil, -----. Mèziéres
    Wishes to know Franklin's direct address before he reveals his object in writing.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 12; A.L.S. 6p.; Carroll, Charles. of Carrollton. Anne Arundel County, Md
    Requesting him to send the enclosed letter to Mr. Carmichael. Events resulting in the loss of the posts of Ticonderoga and Mount Independence. Inaction of Gen. Howe incomprehensible; thinks they will eventually direct their entire force against the state of New York. Hopes for the ultimate success of their struggle for independence, provided they receive the necessary assistance from abroad; greatest apprehensions arise from the depreciation of paper money. Every member of Congress anxious for a confederacy of states; advantages to be derived from such a step. Question of introducing foreign mercenaires. Certain artisans very much needed; have been greatly distressed for want of salt; means being taken to obviate this; high prices paid for the necessaries of life. State of the weather and the crops.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Wickes, Lambert. St. Malo
    Orders from the Judges refusing to let him take cannon, powder or stores on board, or to depart without further instructions from Paris; his indignation at such treament.
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France, I, 126.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 13; A.L. 1p.; Jefferson, Thomas. Virginia
    Recommending to Franklin's kind offices Mr. Thos. Shore, a native of Virginia, who goes to France to establish a proper mercantile correspondence. Virginia has deposited the monarchical and taken up the republican government with the greatest ease; thinks their cause is safe if they can support the credit of their paper; steps to be taken to achieve that result. Outlines the consequences should the British Court come to their senses in time and acknowledge the independence and sovereignty of America. [Conclusion torn off.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?] August 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques. Paris
    Sends M. de Vic to Franklin; his son, M. de Bois Bertrand, crossed to America in July. 1776, as lieutenant-colonel, and was taken a few days afterwards with Gen. Lee; M. de Vic will explain what happened after that; desires that his son shall return to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Raspe, Rudolph Erich. London
    Letters he has written to Franklin; with the last he sent a copy of his fastest literary production. Treated in a despicable manner by certain persons in Germany and England; if he comes to Paris, can Franklin rescue him from that ruin which knaves have attempted to bring upon him. Sends a copy of his late English edition of Born's Mineralogical Letters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 14; A.L.S. 7p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Account of a visit he paid to Amsterdam and of his conversation with the Factor and M. Van Berkel; England's desire to force Holland into an alliance she wishes to form with Russia and Prussia; has M. Van Berkel's word that Amsterdam will never consent to it; his own opinion as to the relations of Holland, England and France; believes the time to be ripe for working and intriguing at Amsterdam. Report received that the houses at Flushing were purchased by some merchants of Dunkirk; their reasons for this.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning a request from M. Flobergue de la Rocatelle [in French, 1 p.] to forward two packets to America, one to Congress, the other to Gen. Washington; will forward them unless he forbids.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Mr. Henry Newman and Mr. Thomas Cushing.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Nicholson, Samuel. St. Malo
    Arrived at St. Malo. Mr. Elliot recommended by Capt. Wickes to go out with him as captain of marines; asks for a commission for him; wrote before for a commission for M. de Manay, at present master of the Dolphin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 August 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Wickes, Lambert. St. Malo
    Recommends Mr. Beaugear and his son to Franklin's kindness; aid they have rendered him in arming and fitting his vessel. Capt. Nicholson's arrival at Nantes with a fine new ship; recommends Mr. Elliot for his captain of marines. Wishes to know how far he may be justifiable in complying with the orders of administration for his governance.